Finding Aid for the John B. Ransom, III Correspondence Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
John B. Ransom, III Correspondence Collection
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0358
.42 linear_feet
Biography
John B. Ransom, III was born September 12, 1920 in Nashville, Tennessee, the son of Marie Litton Howe Ransom and John Bostick Ransom, Jr. He graduated from Wallace University School and attended Vanderbilt University from 1938-1940. He then transferred to the University of the South (Sewanee) and received the B.A. in 1942. He served in the U.S. Army in World War II. After the war he attended Stanford University where he earned an M.A. degree in American Literature. His Master’s Essay at Stanford was an analyis of the writings of Robert Penn Warren. After Stanford he attended Oxford University and the Sorbonne in Paris, France. Later, in Paris he served for ten years as Education Adviser for the Army’s Seine Area Command. In that position he administered a program in which American military and civilian personnel could earn college credits in courses offered by the University of Maryland. After Paris he accepted the position of Director of Admissions at Sewanee where he served for many years. Retiring from that position, he became Secretary of the University until his retirement. He died in Sewanee on March 4, 2000.
Scope and Contents
This small collection (.21 linear feet) is comprised of correspondence to John B. Ransom, III from the following:
C.S. Lewis
Mrs. Robert Lowell (Jean Stafford)
Francis Robinson
Wallace Stegner
Allen Tate
Nancy Tate Wood
Robert Penn Warren
There is other correspondence from Donald Davidson to Marie H. Ransom concerning poems by John B. Ransom, III.
- Incoming Correspondence
  - Lewis, C.S., July 24, 1950 (Folder 1)
  - Lowell, Mrs. Robert T.S. (Jean Stafford), postmark, October 12, 1944 (Folder 1)
  - Robinson, Francis (Folder 2)
  - December 25, 1937 (Folder 2)
  - November 6, 1942 (Folder 2)
  - May 9, 1943 (Folder 2)
  - February 23, 1949 (Folder 2)
  - February 10, 1964 (Folder 2)
  - December 20, 1966 (Folder 2)
  - Stegner, Wallace (Folder 3)
  - January 19, 1966 (Folder 3)
  - August 14, ? (Folder 3)
  - Tate, Allen (Folder 4)
  - Invitation (Folder 4)
  - August 21, 1968 (Folder 4)
  - Program of the Celebration of his 75th Birthday, November 15, 1974 (Folder 4)
  - Nancy Tate Wood on her father’s death, March 26, 1979 (Folder 4)
  - Warren, Robert Penn (Folder 5)
  - Christmas greeting from Cinina and Red Warren, December 1949 (Folder 5)
  - August 15, 1950 (Folder 5)
  - May 2, 1964 (Folder 5)
- Other Correspondence
  - Letter to Marie H. Ransom from Donald Davidson, concerning John B. Ransom’s poems with comments by Davidson (letter and 16 pages of poems), November 21,1944 (Folder 6)